welcome
uh to the philosopher king queens i
almost said kings that's terrible
queens because perhaps um
it doesn't there hasn't been that many
philosopher queens before and
you you um you women are the first
perhaps philosopher queens ever is that
is that correct
i'm not sure we're coming you know in
the lineage of camille paglia i don't
know if she would call herself the queen
but she's certainly the philosopher
androgen so
um i think we definitely have a lineage
to
um you know bow our heads to so
not the only ones but quite rare quite
rare
quite rare right there there's been
philosophers
who are women in history but they are
quite rare aren't they
um so you tell me a little bit i'll be
you know before i introduce you
douchey tell me about that lineage
because that might be a good place to
start
i'm gonna get my fans
okay here we go yeah rachel do you want
to talk about
um there's been a lineage for
a while um when we think about
like joan of arc we think about
classical opera
we think about the amazon tribe
there is a lot of philosopher queen
energy
when we think about cleopatra
when we think about mythology in general
and everyone from medusa to
aphrodite we have different
philosopher queens what camille paglia
did
was formalize it in her magnum opus
sexual persona which inspired a bit of a
cult following
um among i guess dissident
academic types cultural theologians
creative people who didn't see gender
as a binary construct but that were also
not
you know social justice you know or even
trans necessarily but like this this
lineage this philosopher queen
type and um correct to say that it's
it's somewhat of a hidden lineage like
it pops up sometimes but
but it's more of a hidden lineage than
say let's the more explicit
philosopher king lineage if we could
talk about that
yeah i i think it would be hidden
because
the well i mean you've got plato's
republic
you know socrates it's always like
symposiums um and
there aren't very many female
philosophers in general
um like the most recent one i can think
of
um well you know the ones that we hosted
at the philosopher queen panel
you know um like native power and uh
alyssa
i can think of donna haraway before that
who wrote the cyborg manifesto um
but who who did we really have before
that like maybe
hannah ardent i hope i forgot
yeah she was she was around early too
yeah
yeah there's a french philosopher i live
in france called simon vale
not the most very famous she's wonderful
she's one an amazing incredible
and uh she's not as she's not well
enough known i i don't think
and um yeah that's one that
made me think i never really would have
thought of medusa as being a philosopher
but
but but uh but maybe
it's like the lineage you know the
olympians like the imagery
the archetype yeah that accompany
um you know what you guys are about um
okay well why don't why don't i just
uh give a short introduction and then
i'll give you the floor okay
how does that sound okay so um
so we have uh
rachel hayward you've written the um
the manifesto of the philosopher queens
um
and uh and you and raven
um do a lot of you know conferences and
discussions
at the stoa and other places and
and um you've worked with
um you know the alexa
you've created something called the
alexa salon um
rachel you're an entrepreneur and you're
into into virtual reality and art and
fashion and philosophy
and you wrote a book called the new art
rite
and i want to i want to question you a
little bit about that very provocative
um title and then raven it says it
you're a socialite
i thought that was that was a hilarious
um
bio that you wrote um a socialite
in a mosaic of independent intellectual
milieus ranging from justin murphy's
indie thinkers to peter lindberg's estoa
she hosts interview guests at the stoa
and is currently developing
uh philosophy of the ovum secrecy
and marriage okay so so
all of that is is very interesting and
wonderful and um
i'll just give you the floor and say
welcome
to parallax we're we're new this is our
sixth parallax lecture
uh we've had several several elections
we've had we're have some good ones
coming up and we've had
a few with hanzi and and
uh roe eshelman and um
and uh alexander bard and so anyway
welcome to
to our our new sort of parallax movement
and please have the floor
and uh for let's say 45 minutes and then
we'll come back with
uh uh i'll ask you a few questions and
i'll then i'll open up the floor for
everybody else
if that sounds good for you guys yeah
that sounds great
yes um so we're gonna begin by uh
having rachel kind of explain like where
the manifesto came from
and then we're gonna go through and kind
of have a bit of a dialogue about where
that
ended up going and what the future may
hold
for kind of building a movement of women
who are
armed with reason and logic
and also this like kind of libidonal
drive
right like to to try and charge
ourselves to
go forth into the world and create a
philosophical movement of philosopher
queens
so rachel tell us what's the origin of
the queen manifesto so i wrote the
philosopher
playing manifesto to carve out a niche
that i felt had always existed but had
been kind of obscured
and that women like us needed to get
together
because i had seen two
polar extremes i had seen the
ultra traditionalist conservative women
on one end
and i had seen these social
activists extreme misfeminists
on the other end and i started to think
well
what about the femme fatales what about
the women who occupy
that space in between what about the
women that transcend
these labels of traditionalists or
social activists
what about women like camille paglia who
wrote about this pathway
about this aesthetic exploration
about this creative invocation
of the tonic the hidden the
mysterious the forbidden the
shadow if you will and
the manifesto i i can read some of it
here
we are the rising of the divine feminine
in its tonic form
we are philosopher queens we blast open
the doors of perception
and explore the deepest areas of our
minds and
spirits we revive the power of chaos
and her original essence as our new
order begins to take
shape we are philosopher queens
we are the origin of every story
and the origin was a big
part for me about the
origin of these works of art
about these works of literature about
these empires
uh about these civilizations well where
did they
originate from the divine mother
and how did the mother come in to be
through struggle and that struggle
led to birth and that birth led to
entirely
new worlds entirely new species
and that's why i talk about the origin
because
i think that people often forget about
the origin
they sometimes think about feminism as a
hashtag self-care hashtag boss girl
movement um some people just think about
feminism now
as the same thing as black lives matter
and trans and it's all intersectionality
you know um they they all just mush it
all together
and a lot of the work of
these great philosophers and artists and
musicians
has been obscured by this modern
polarization so when writing the
manifesto i meant to speak to these
things
to speak to the these women who maybe
were feeling disenfranchised
who didn't have a place that they really
felt that they could be comfortable
on being expressive is the women that
they
they are you know they maybe felt that
they needed to hide
the more expressive parts of themselves
they needed to tone themselves
down to make themselves more traditional
or they needed to become an activist and
you know social justice types to getting
with that other end or
you know boss girl you know hashtag like
posting
selfies on instagram if they're you know
bathtub
with the flower bonnet or whatever the
chakra of the healing types
do so right so
yeah it's reactionary but probably we
all know
i'm talking about um so you know what
about the rest of us right
who are we who are we um and the more i
thought about it the more that we're
philosopher queens because we question
everything and we're not in it
for the fam or the money we're in for
the knowledge
and that's what all of us have in common
we are
seekers of knowledge we are seekers
of new realms new possibilities
and like camilcalia we understand
the cycle that it isn't all one
or the other but sometimes there's
apollo that sometimes there's dionysus
that sometimes it's
a chaotic stream of inspiration
and beauty and sometimes it's a very
ordered
hierarchical building you know
of structure sometimes it's both
and sometimes these cycles revolve you
know just
like spangler was talking about with
civilizations that's how
gender is true um throughout the ages
there are many women who would have
defined
as one thing who have defined as
something else just because the era
is different one error is amazon is
another
powers liberal activist and one
aries cleopatra is a another
activist rulers dancer as
the times change
the people change and as the people
change
the society changes the culture changes
new archetypes develop and new
archetypes transform
now raven has been
very encouraging about the philosopher
queen
manifesto i mean she was so encouraging
about it she's like we should turn it
into
a panel at the stoa and i
felt like i had to say yes because i've
been going to panels like the stoa
i'd been i did my own panel at the store
about aesthetics and building an
aesthetic movement um and i'd gone to a
lot of ravens panels
where she was hosting just really
interesting guests and
really amazing topics so i'm like sure
i'd love to do this panel and then
it kind of took on a life of its own
yeah absolutely i feel like there's
something else as well i mean rachel
like i was following rachel the great
rachel haywire
um before when i was just listening to
podcasts
um about a year ago and we met in new
york city
and there was just like explosions
of like synergy and synchronicity
and we've been working on projects ever
since and i think that that was kind of
like the first
you know there's this individual right
we are individuals we are kind of
separated from one another as as
as women as philosopher queens um and
you know finding rachel was this moment
of like the beginning of
building a tribe right this like moment
of a dyad
forming uh where we could begin to
explore ideas together and also appear
in in public which i think is also part
of what's interwoven
into the manifesto i think this is
something that rachel brings
that's really unique is this drive to
expose
to expose ideas um which i think is
inherently connected to the willingness
to take risks
the willingness to stand for what you
believe in
and to go out there and piss people off
which is of course another
aspect of going against uh the grain
of conformity of mimesis which is
another aspect of the manifesto
is pointing out the memetic aspects to
the groups
that have been emerging around women's
rights or women's interests
um the kind of matriarchies that are
forming are kind of gathering around
certain polarities in terms of these
these like as you
as you describe like hashtags right so
we have like this kind of trad wife
thing
uh we also have this like social justice
thing both groups have conservative
elements
right where there's this kind of
reactionary like we don't want to stare
at the phallus
we don't want to face the disgusting
aspects of not only ourselves
but also what it is
to face the world today what it is to
face
uh genuine real issues of
misogyny and sexism but also to
accept what men have done for the world
i mean i think that this is one of the
things that uh really drew me to camille
paglia when she like opens her book and
she's like
you know if civilization had been left
to women we'd all be living in grass
huts
and i think that starting there is like
this brilliant confrontation
of the differences between men and women
and the fact that there is this dynamic
between these
these these forms these two different
forms
that are distinct and have
different polarities that they embody
which is also why
even speaking about the feminine or
speaking about the masculine
has legitimacy um where
that that dimorphism is actually
embodying principles that exist not only
merely within biology but you know the
ideas of like chaos versus order
um but i think the other thing is not to
be reactionary against
the concept of the androgen just because
there are people in the social justice
world who are kind of
emphasizing trans issues over the issues
of these
these two polarities right so we have to
also speak about the androgen
and the different aspects of what it is
to be androgynous
um the androgynous aspect that is about
becoming adult becoming a synthesis um
and the androgynous aspect that is a
regression or an infantilization which
camille paglia really
lays out uh very well in her book sexual
personae in terms of what a decadent
androgen um emerges as so
all of these things have been kind of
mulling around between rachel and i
over the over almost a year that we've
known each other
and i think you know her bringing forth
this manifesto
kind of just like pierced into the the
discourse or the currents
um in order to get both of us to just
begin
to work together um begin to kind of
form a dyad
and try and basically through
example attract other women to what
we're doing
um rather than kind of having this you
know
um drive to like you know
like get people to join us through some
sort of
ad campaign it's like no if you we're
gonna lead by example we're gonna
we're gonna talk about these things
openly and without fear
and if you wanna join us you're welcome
um but we're not gonna chase after you
you know it's this is is what we're
doing
um yeah i don't know rachel if you want
to respond to any of that yeah well i
mean chasing
after somebody it's always the wrong
idea if you notice but none of these
recruitment groups are
effective on none of these campaigns to
get people
to vote for a certain thing or being
very well received
now during the election you can see
everybody
angrily tweeting about how they're sick
of getting
calls about who to vote for um it's
because we don't like things that
are trying too hard um and i say
in the manifesto i'm going to quote
another part
that which we do not reveal becomes that
which the world desires
so it's the hidden element what we keep
to ourselves
that becomes the object of fixation
from the society from
from the other that which we don't
reveal that people come
to us for what people
are interested in what is intriguing to
them
not what we have right in front of them
because what often happens when you put
something
in front of people is that
they get into a linguistic tit-for-tat
their mind immediately goes to
preconceived biases that they have
and they're already fixated on defining
something based on their own
models of reality without really looking
into other possibilities so
by creating an element
of mystery and
keeping it sacred more people
are drawn to the mystique that
has been repressed um and not not just
repressed
um but relegated to the shadow realm
because women aren't really supposed to
be into certain things i mean this is
where the philosopher queen
part comes into there are certain
philosophies that
women aren't supposed to be into
when was the last time you heard about a
a woman into heidegger
when when i met raven one of the things
that impressed me about her was that she
was a woman who
was studying heidegger because i don't
need very many women who are even
willing
to like acknowledge heidegger you know
i'm so
you know um what about the the women who
are
into um somebody like nick land you know
um there was the
ccru there were the xeno feminists and
they were sadie plant
right um in the ireland but
these are obscure names these are their
small names among
our circle there weren't very many women
who
were interested in looking at these
these darker
philosophical explorations you don't
need very many
women who are into nietzsche
you certainly don't meet very many women
who are into a lot of
political things um you know like you
have the
conservative moms right um and then you
have the liberal activists um
well what about other realms of politics
there just aren't very many women who
are participating in these things they
feel that they can because it's
unfeminine
they feel like it's on lady life or
that they don't belong in the discourse
because that's for the men to
discuss um you know when we think about
how men went out and hunted
you know um but women have been
discoursing since the beginning of time
and people seem to forget that
and i think it's time for us to remember
sure i think it's a good question
um why aren't there
more women um especially because you
know what i've observed is that women
who
are into philosophy also tend to be into
intersectionality so women who are in
the humanities
um they're often into queer theory and
they're often going off into
yes kind of frankfurt school kind of you
know post-modernist post-structuralist
and there's this intertwining with
political
activism um and
while i think that you know there seems
to be a lot of momentum in that
direction
the fact of it is there are more things
to think about than political ideology
um and i think particularly
as we are confronting the changes of
our reality due to technological shifts
um we have to we have to get outside of
frameworks that we've inherited
particularly ones that have mass appeal
i mean i've been thinking a lot about um
you know exodus like bard's exodus
um you know obviously the concept of
exit um or
what i've been uh i've been listening to
for medics which is another fantastic
podcast
hosted by mada nomad um and he has been
bringing up the concept the archetype of
the anarch
right so as opposed to anarchist which
is a political ideology the anarch who
stands
outside of society and dares to think
for himself and typically himself
really i mean i think that there are
certain kinds of personality traits that
you find clustered more often in men and
women
anti-social behavior is more often
a male trait and i think that you need
the capacity
to say i don't care about assimilating
into society
i am being anti-social um i'm not
falling into
what you know ted kasinski calls like
kind of the leftist
over socialization right i'm standing
outside of that
and i'm defining for myself what i what
i think your observation
through kind of a cold analysis and i
think that's almost necessary
in a time where there's so much
confusion there's so much chatter
you know in our memetic environments so
much disinformation and manipulation and
if we're going to see clearly which i
think is also part of what
bart is invoking in terms of this
seeking of the authentic phallus
how are we going to penetrate
and order all of this kind of flat
you know array of information and ideas
that weren't
being kind of awash in this feminine
principle of the internet
i mean it's it's it really is like kind
of the medium
of our existence now and we're kind of
uh
confronting this been thinking a lot
about the adam and eve story right like
there's a certain amount you become
conscious you eat from the fruit
and you be you realize your nakedness
and you hide
in shame i think that that's what we're
doing
you know and i think women in particular
uh like at least
you know maybe not in particular in a
you know in an emphasizing sort of way
but like the issues of women are
particularly interesting to me
um because as a woman you know i'm also
seeking
relationships with other women and uh
also seeking to build a matriarchy
which has completely dissolved um that
is intergenerational uh which is like
totally unraveled uh we don't have that
you know lineage of cohesion uh which is
exactly why rachel you know and i are
you know coming together is so important
but what are we you know what are we
what are we doing like what are how are
we facing these issues
how are we thinking about uh these these
changes in our world and going back to
first principles and staring at things
with bravery looking at what has been on
earth
rather than hiding our nakedness in in
in our shame you know um we
we are kind of given this task
i think to face you know what science
has unearthed what psychoanalysis is
on earth what like the observation of
the 20th century and all of its horrors
have unearthed what birth control has
done for women
how women coming into the public sphere
has changed
social and political dynamics how
now we're dealing with mixed like co-ed
offices and how that kind of creates
tension
between the sexes um and also
just the concept that comes from
feminism of a woman being essentially
interiorly male with just the
form of a man of a woman with with
breasts
and you know with the rounded body of a
woman and and to operate as if just this
kind of cartesian
male subject um which causes a lot of
tension if that's not
how you that's not true if that's not
true and you're operating as if that is
true
then a lot of misery will come of that
and i think we're seeing
we're seeing that as well um and then of
course
the basic issues of the human condition
you know
envy and bitterness
and despair and you know
jealousy and all of these kind of
emotional
aspects of what it is to live in a
community and to see the things that
other people have and to want them
but to not admit that you want them and
i think that's also something that's
tearing apart communities of women
particularly because we we've really and
i think feminism has really
played a role in this um has pushed
aside the role of the mother
and has made it something lesser
you know you hear a woman who gets
married at maybe 23 or something and
you're
you're like oh what a what a pity why
would she do that
you know she has her whole life ahead of
her why would she get married
and have children and what if women want
to do that
like what if they want to get married
and have children
like how would that rub against them
that their society
is trying to make them conform to this
ideal
of being you know a an economic
subject so i think that all of these
dynamics
are essential for women themselves to be
talking about in a very lucid way um
and so far i mean at least in my
experience
where i've seen people discussing these
things honestly
is not in communities of women it's in
communities of men
because men are also in a in an
impoverishment
because women don't know what the hell
they're doing
men also don't know what they're doing
but you know they can at least see from
the outside
that there's something going on with the
women that's causing
you know issues in terms of these these
polarities
coming together um the sex is coming
together and being able to interact in
harmonious and different ways different
ways
we're struggling with plurality you know
we have
we cannot seem to grab grapple with or
accept the idea that difference does not
mean better or worse
you know um that the feminine principle
isn't somehow
subordinate or like you know bad
or even different different doesn't
mean better worse just because
gender is changing doesn't mean that we
shouldn't
look at gender that we should pretend
like gender doesn't exist that we should
ignore
gender no we should engage with gender
we should explore gender
um we should like raven was talking
about you know a lot of women feeling
like they have this this female form
you know i'm but they're not really you
know women
in inside um well first of all what does
it mean to be a woman inside because the
definition of that
keeps changing you know what what does
it mean
to to be a woman does it mean to
be a mother does it mean to be a ceo
does it mean to be a mother and a ceo
to be neither does it mean to be soft
and sensitive does it mean to be dark
and
powerful does it mean to be
beautiful does it mean to be intense
what does it mean to be a woman does it
mean to be hysterical
does it mean to be neurotic does it mean
to be a sex goddess
does it mean to be anti-sex what does it
mean to be
a woman and people
really seem to have a lot of different
answers to that question
um now when rhythm was talking about
a lot of women they want to get married
and have kids
obviously that is fine and nobody should
ever say like oh you're not a
real feminist because you want to get
married and have kids um
i would take this a little further i
would say that if you want to be married
and have kids
that you should be able to be a boss
girl if you want to
say you want a thriving career and you
want children
is that suddenly off limits say you want
to be married
and don't have children and that you
want to
be a dancer because you like dancing
you want to participate in
a sexual type of expression
what's wrong with that say you want to
have kids
you want to get married and
you want to start a company
why not right why are all these
limitations
being placed whether it's the feminists
or the
the trad lives social justice boss girl
why
why are they all so restrictive and
philosopher queens we are not
restrictive we
are open we seek knowledge we're
philosophers
and if you go back in history
you can hear about all of these other
women that have sought knowledge um
some of them have been obscured you're
right um but some of them have not um
amelia earhart
you know what whatever happened to her
now she flew that plane and
she disappeared why did she disappear
has anybody really
looked into that you know um whatever
happened
to cleopatra's children
right what what was the next step
in egypt right um really look into that
too much
um what about kali
the goddess of chaos and destruction how
was the mythology
for kali invented is this just the kali
yuga
or is this a an archetype of
this cycle of birth and rebirth of
creation
destruction creation destruction
what does it mean to be a woman and why
are so many things
off of limits
yeah i mean there's even
there's even a question about like
whether or not the word woman is even
a good one you know or like
something worth even you know keeping
alive so
it's yeah it's a it's a i think the
question of limitations
is is definitely important and
um i think that it's very easy
especially
in an era where we have these like alien
thoughts
that come come into our minds um
and we want to conform ourselves to
these visions that come from the outside
um and i think this is the this is the
power
of the the nieces that comes in from
behind
and kind of channels your your energy or
your vision
um but it is not your own you are not
authoring it
um it's coming from the forces of others
and
this kind of purging of the voices of
these aliens i think is like one of
these
initial steps to becoming a free thinker
and of course that's i mean i think why
um why philosopher queens why not just
hashtag queen you know what is this why
are we
even bringing in philosophy i mean i
think that um both rachel and i
are deeply committed to ideas above all
else
um freedom of thought and thinking
aggressively independently seeking
antagonism
you know not taking it personally if
someone disagrees with you
experiencing like the um
the the charge i mean i think there's
there's this libidonal aspect to
engaging
in the world of ideas um and i think
women can bring that charge
um they can kind of bring the gestalt of
their sexuality
into the sphere that is um
fiery with the discussion of what it
means
you know not merely to be a woman what
it means but it means to be human what
it means to interact with technology
um what is the future you know there's
this very regressive kind of retro
um movement i think that's happening
but in a reaction to the confusion
um that the human psyche is kind of
going through in response to the chaos
of our technological environment
and to stand still
to purge all of this kind of you know
mimetic desire and to
try to chart your own path forward um i
think is to kind of rise above
these like waves um of chaos
and to investigate principally
i mean i'm i feel very early i mean i'm
you know i i'm young and like just
beginning to learn
about all of these things and so i think
not drawing conclusions too quickly
um is part of what feels important um
and to be
and to be open like you're saying rachel
and and to consider
ideas and to not recoil from them
because they're uncomfortable
um not to recoil from criticism because
it makes you feel bad
you know it's like getting into that
zone
where you can be brave and you can
commit
to your own ideas but you can also face
the scrutiny of others um that's i mean
that's what it is to be on the front
lines in terms of intellect
and intellectual battling um
and men seem to be doing this all the
time uh at least in these little
communities
whether or not it's very good or not i
think is kind of dependent um there's
definitely a lot of like circle jerking
i think that happens
but there are genuinely um
generative male communities of
philosophy
and i think that you know
once the women find we'll find those
places we'll start bringing our own
thoughts to that world and um
i don't know what will happen i mean
like like we were talking about this is
new
like women being in this position um
at least within the kind of history that
we
we are familiar with is it's novel it's
novel and so there's still a lot to
investigate
and ask questions about and i want us to
open ourselves to those questions
and uh see what we find
you know principally yeah
there there have been some attempts
you know um this is kind of an obscure
example um
but i was an industrial music producer
growing up so kind of like
goth electronic music i produced on my
laptop
and a few synthesizers and the genre
industrial which is kind of like an
offshoot of goth and punk um with a
little bit of a
cyberpunk element um it's very masculine
the music was masculine and the outfits
were masculine
like big stompy boots you know and like
very militant post-apocalyptic gear
you know um on the dance floor and it
had a very
masculine element um but there were some
women in the scene too and
we loved the music all the same and we
started to make our own music
um and i formed a record label for women
in the goth industrial scene
women in the darker subcultures you know
i formed
an alliance you know um the vanguard
if you will um and i think that many
things like this have occurred
in the past but maybe they they just
don't um
really get uh recognition um i remember
like
i read a book about female futurists
you know most people only know male
futurist and you know the future is
manifesto it's
misogynistic so you know women are
dissuaded from like even getting into
futurism like at all
like period um yeah
so so that there's a lot of stuff that
women just feel
like is forbidden and off the table
and well i'm like commemorative i don't
feel like anything should be for them
like we need to get to the inner core
of the spirit of this
dionysus this occupation
of our souls our bodies our minds
culture
the universe life the world how how do
we interact
with the apollo what happens when we
become the apollonian what happens when
we become the matriarchs
what happens when society is flipped
upside down
when we don't know what gender is
anymore
what do we do then we carry
on a torch of philosopher queens
we carry on a torch of self-expression
and beauty
without limitation we
carry on a torch of the divinity
of the self which is not strictly
feminine or
strictly masculine it is perhaps
androgynous
like alexander var talks about he says
androgyny
is close to shamanism perhaps
philosopher queens are channeling
something shamanistic
we are between worlds we
are bridges between the feminine and the
masculine
occupying both realms and exploring
each gender yet defining as
female defining as queens defining as
women
who are seeking knowledge
cool does that seem like a good place to
jump in or
i thought that was brilliant yeah i
thought that was a brilliant conclusion
so women seeking knowledge yeah i
as well
um i made a few notes here but
i'm kind of going to throw away my notes
and just say what
comes to my mind uh and maybe we can
have a short conversation and then i'll
open up everything to
the the few people here who are here
um i was thinking as you were talking i
was
thinking about how limited are our
personas
are in this culture how we have such
cliche versions of everything um
and it occurs to me that that's kind of
what what
this this boundaries that you you guys
are trying to break
like i was reading tyson yakapura's book
and he talked about how his
how in his indigenous village the women
were really tough and they got into
street fights and
and the men were kind of sensitive and
very very very soft and and uh
um you know and and it just occurred to
me that that we we
we're kind of living in a time where
we're in this global culture where where
gender has become a prison of some kind
um and also i just wanted to i wanted to
say that
my own personal experience is that you
know in my in my youth
i i was i was a musician i played in
bands and people in bands have long hair
and
they they kind of adore women like we we
worship
women on some level in our 20s men and
they even try to dress like them
and and uh you know we see that in in
popular
culture and um and i think
later as i i became older i started
becoming interested in masculinity again
like
i didn't give a about you know what
that was before
um so it's interesting i wanna i i feel
like the culture has just flipped over
on its side or something where
where people are now looking for like uh
uh they've been sort of shattered in
every direction and all they have
is cliche models of of what masculine
and feminine could be so
they're going back to try to find a you
know a more
deeper archetype does that make any
sense can can you riff off anything i
i said there
uh yeah no i mean i
i mean it seems like this is a perennial
issue
right where people seek outward guidance
for who they should ought to become
right i think um the fracturing of
traditional roles
and also just the kind of
like the the the internet itself just
being this kind of importation device
where you you are being formed your
cognition and your experience
of your thoughts is being trained
by this being this thing that's like
maximizing for your attention on screen
and that fracturing as well kind of
causes the shattering of the mirror
um and then of course people are seeking
to conform to those
communities and so they find themselves
trying to model um you know instagram
influencers
popular hashtags um it's it's
very i think it's very i like uh
very much a root in celebrity worship
idolatry um you know kind of a
scrambling to form identity and
a lot of it is very adolescent in my
eyes
where it's like we don't want to become
like our parents
there's this like elder kind of phobia
you know
and so we we seek to become like our
peers
and this is extending beyond adolescence
into people who are like in their 30s
and even 40s yeah
that's the lack of transmission right uh
you know and the lack of a vertical
culture where you have
you know you have elders up here and you
have young up here and they aspire to
move up to to embody the the elder uh
it seems like young people are just
imitating each other
you know i'm a teacher and i notice my
students are
uh you know they don't have they don't
have in models of imitation except for
each other they're just they're just
it's a kind of narcissistic fog or
something
and the mind-blowing thing is there are
people in their 40s and 50s who are
trying to mimic
year olds oh yeah wow i am just blown
away by this
it's it's like crazy you know you see
i mean like these kind of advertising
campaigns for different social justice
pursuits and i'm seeing like old women
you know getting involved in this stuff
um so there's definitely this idea i
think
um that the children are gonna save us
they have the right ideas
and we're gonna get behind them with our
signs and we're gonna let them leave the
charge
yeah the children's crusade it's like
something like that yeah
yes you know the children of god will
save us you know
uh and it's all it's all kind of this um
deification of the political
you know secular society has just kind
of formed itself within the political
narrative as being of the utmost
importance
and everything else is like to bow down
to this
um very matriarchal force of attempting
to kind of take care of everyone um
through the state and it's it appears on
the surface to be very patriarchal but
it is also very matriarchal
exactly yeah there's all these weird
paradoxes that you just have to be able
to like
first of all you have to be able to
understand paradox right which is in and
of itself
that's a big one that's such a big one
you have to understand paradox you have
to understand nuance you
have to understand the ebb and flow of
gender civilization you have to
understand the hegelian dialect you
can't get stuck in one brown because if
you do then you're not able to see the
other side and if you can't
see the other side then you can't see
anything that's around you
you're you're just stuck in a little
tunnel of
your little echo chamber um and all of
this
copying that we see on instagram
um from the social justice movements and
from the the boomers
to the millennials to the zoomers um
that this lack of originality this fear
of going outside the grain you know i'm
the fear of being shamed
you know the fear of being kicked out of
one's
tribe you know um like i think is the
big reason
for all this mimesis and
jealousy you know um of women copying
one another because they just
want to fit in and they don't want to be
looked at and scrutinized and where
raven and i we love being scrutinized we
love
critique we love argument um that is
part of being
philosophers this is part of being a
philosopher we don't want to be treated
differently because we're women we don't
want to be like coddled and
told that we're special just because of
our gender we want to be
known for our theories and our thoughts
and
our creations and um
even the whole idea of like do we need a
female philosopher movement i'm
even like mixed on that even though i
started the
philosopher queen manifesto because we
don't want to just be known
for being women we want to be known for
what we create
um and then if you think about it that
was actually like one of the original
motivations of
feminism but what is feminism now is it
burning bras
is it you know i'm going to a sex
club is is it body positivity
like what does does feminism even mean
now is this anti-feminist
relevant is that just feminism on the
same coin yeah different sides like
what what is even going on here when you
guys were talking at the very beginning
uh we got
attacked by a troll i don't know if
you've noticed i saw that
there was these horrific you know
messages
like women should die in really terrible
are slaves
really and uh so i apologize to expose
you again i was trying to get rid of it
but i didn't know how and i finally
figured it out
i wasn't sure if that was um
like a troll of mine it's nobody who's
here so it must be somebody i guess on
facebook or i don't know how i don't
know how that
maybe but i i wonder about like being
exposed to that kind of thing
how that that affects you because you
know as a guy it just doesn't
does that sort of thing doesn't come my
way so
so i'm wondering i'm wondering how you
how you
you know camille paglia had a very
heroic attitude towards that it's just
you know be strong right be strong women
and strong men and
i wonder you know how does that
how does that you know what do you what
do you do with that
i think rachel's probably experienced a
lot more of that than i have so i get i
gotta get out of it
because i'm very i don't
i'm not a social conservative so i have
a lot of
men on the right i'm not a conservative
man
who just tell me to shut up and have a
kid like
pretty regularly i mean this is simply
because i
interact with conservative ideas on a
philosophical level
you know um i can be a conservative
you know philosophically and be
conservative
aesthetically um but if i'm not
conservative in my lifestyle because i
don't have a kid
who am i to to talk about certain ideas
at all so i definitely get a
a lot of harassment for men um and
and women and trad lives there are those
types that
they don't like me very much and that
that's not even mentioning like the
antique boss and the social justice
activists like i don't even mention them
um
i just it was in one year and out the
other
it's not relevant to me because it
doesn't affect me
okay because i don't take it personally
because that's their
issue and then that's it that's the
issue
not to say that it isn't a burden
you know not to say that it isn't
energetically expensive
to deal with that kind of attention but
i think that
this is not something that is merely an
issue for women
it seems like women may get
more kind of attention from multiple
directions i think that
rachel is pointing out something really
important that
not only will men come after you but
women will come after you too
so it's it's definitely
difficult to stand against the crowd
um and that but that's you know that's
if you have something to say i mean it's
it's
this is once again perennial like the
mob right
goes after those who stand for
the future i mean the prophet right we
think of you know if you think about
christ
right like the mob is what like
forces you know the government to put
him on the cross you know it's the mob
that destroys the future
and it's in that destruction of
the prophet that the future actually
comes to be
um and that playing around with those
archetypes and understanding that
to speak the truth is not some sort of
lackadaisical
like you know kind of fun thing that you
do on the weekends
this is like sacrifice this is something
that you do because you care about it
and you put yourself on the line you
have skin in the game you know
like rachel has skin in the game for
what she says i'm beginning to get out
there
you know and say the things um and
starting to you know kind of see that
black will come my way in order to do
that but i think
i think that's part of why like an
alliance is also
super powerful um that having yeah you
need community don't you
you need you need a strong community to
support you if you're going to
you know say something that will if
you're uh
you know that will that will offend the
the super collective ego or whatever of
the society
i i'd like to say something like very
contrarian now
about our own community
in our own community like there aren't
very many women who have a fiery element
like i am a fiery woman
my raven is inspiring i mean i like
got a lot of fiery friends um but it
seems like the majority of women in this
community
are very earthy there's nothing wrong
with earth
nothing wrong with it um but it seems to
be like the
exclusive element in the the spear that
we're in for
for women besides me and raven and the
women that we've been brought into this
game
i mean the hippie kind of earth goddess
kind of archetype
seems to be uh you know in ascendance at
the moment again
or something like that right whereas the
entire radical urban
type is is is um
yeah yeah there is about like radical or
urban but expressive
and vitalistic intense
and metaphysical occult
and knowledge so you guys celebrate the
the dark that i mean
rachel especially you celebrate the the
dark in the dark
archetypes and perhaps these archetypes
we've talked about this in our last
conversation um
are lacking in in in a protestant
society
in an angled society especially it's
more present here in france i think in
the catholic tradition but even then
there's this sort of uh
there's the the mother mary images are
very a very
um benevolent and divine and beauty you
know beautiful or
whereas whereas this there's this fierce
other
feminine archetype which you find in
india and in most places of the world
which seems to be quite repressed in in
the contemporary culture would you agree
with that
yeah i think so i mean i think that this
gets into
issues of how christianity has dealt
with
the issue of sex you know
um and the fact that instead of creating
some sort of
uh tradition or i mean you have tantra
right in other cultures right there
these other kind of dimensions of how
sex has been
explored and organized in order to
reduce the memetic
uh contagion effects which can cause
this ricocheting of jealousy and envy
and
and violence in the community that can
come that can come from like
being interested in uh the same woman or
the same kind of sexual prospects
um dangerous certainly uh christianity i
think has just moved to suppress
um and it has an infantilizing aspect to
it i think
as well where we all become children we
all get kind of pushed into the
androgynous state of being
you know the virginia mother um and
the virgin of jesus christ and somehow
that support
we can maybe conflate that with a kind
of memetic
goal like we ought to be that way when
in fact like
the libidinal energy the drive that
comes from
sexual expression is what moves us you
know it's what gets us to
to suppress our neuroticism i mean that
is huge
to suppress your neuroticism and to take
a risk
you know and to maybe lose and to deal
with failure you know the other thing
about it is like
can you confront the fact that if you
risk yourself if you put yourself on the
line that you may fail
and that you have to stand to be judged
by others for your failure and you have
to get up again
and try you know like that type of
behavior activity um i think when you
have low neuroticism
and more anti-social personality traits
it's much easier to just do that and of
course that clusters
men over women um and then there's the
few women
uh that have that happen to have these
personality traits
uh and i think that that's maybe what
rachel's speaking to architecturally
in terms of fieriness right just being
like
throwing caution to the wind and going
out and
doing things i mean simone bay is like a
crazy example of a woman who was just
like she would go and work in factories
and things like that
you know and and uh this
frail anorexic woman went to the front
lines of war
and tried to fight you know like this
woman was so
they wouldn't let her fight in the end
right so she died alone in a hospital in
england
because they wouldn't let her go out and
she just she was that she had a
incredible almost joan of arc type of oh
absolutely nice spirit right yeah
absolutely yeah fighting the fighting
spirit in women
what what has happened to that um i
think of a lot of bands
like the plasmatics punk fan lead singer
came on stage with a giant mohawk on a
tank and just
started going off you know sparks
came out on stage with giant machinery
wendy or williams 70s punk band
they were pretty much the first punk
girl band
to really have a female fronted vocalist
um
i love them um i think about like kathy
acker
she was a post structuralist writer um
she's a feminist but she wasn't like a
the second wave
burn your broth i missed she wasn't like
a third wave like sex worker
transgenders feminism feminist
she was just really into sex and really
into self-expression and really into
breaking down conceptions of gender um
and she did it her own way it wasn't
about being a part of a group or
a collective it wasn't about some some
populist
herd it was about the exploration of
the self right um donna haraway
who wrote the cyborg manifesto she wrote
about how
identity was something that could be
played with about how aligning
with people just because of their gender
or their race or their class wasn't
enough to really unify people well
what needed to happen was people that
had similar
ideas needed to unify based on common
interests
and based on common knowledge you know
um
it's not about like we're all this same
thing it's about how we all have this
idea you know we're philosopher once we
have an idea um you know and of course
donna haraway took a lot of crap she got
put on trial
you know i'm wendio williams seems like
there's a lot at stake
right for a fiery type of woman right um
there's a lot of a lot of you know
whereas um
i i know that um raven mentioned the
tantric tradition and i i know that in
you know in india and and
tibet there's certain very powerful
women who are teachers who are
you know revered right there they're
they're but but they're not usually in
they're not they're not they don't have
they're usually hidden they're they're
called the hidden lineage they're very
you have to you have to um you have to
find them they're not
you know whereas you know i guess it's
just male people tend to be
um tend to be out there in the front uh
you know with their
uh with their voice whereas
it's more rare for a woman to to come
have this fiery kind of passion and come
out into the
into the marketplace and to have
something to say
yeah big big time i mean i need more of
that yeah
i do think a lot of the
sir go ahead oh i was just gonna say i
mean we need more of it but i wouldn't
expect there to be a lot of it
i mean like also to expect women to be
that which they are not i think is also
part of the issue
with what's going on today not only with
just like feminism
and the pressure on little girls to save
the world
you know like take on the mantle of of
like
empowering women and taking down the
patriarchy it's like
not every woman is motivated to do that
and if she thinks that she's there's
this gap between being this like
powerful figure who takes on the world
and
who you are as just a normal little
person
in the world who's like wants to take
care of your of your community of your
family
like none of all of those things i mean
generally has been diminished
like care for the core for the hearth
for the world around you has become
secondary
to celebrity status to appearing
like cool and aloof and uh you know to
be working for the greatest
good but like are you like really
you know you're like tweeting like what
are you doing for your community
like nothing and i think i think
part of it is too like
i think women are busy i think that's
also why we don't see them in some of
these communities
women are busy they're doing and so
they don't have time to around and
talk
especially if they have a career and
children you know
super woman to be managing and taking
care of the home
and giving attention to your children
the attention of mother particularly in
those first
kind of five years of life is so
powerful for the child it directs
child to see what is valuable and
important
you have to prioritize that if you're a
mother
i think so too yeah i mean i i might i
have a one-year-old right now and
my wife's been at home with the
one-year-old for a year
right and because she's had had the
chance to take time off
work um i think it would be terrible i
mean
and that's how most people live right
they just it's careerism right they go
you know and they
drop the kid off at the daycare and so
in that sense i feel like i i i feel
some sympathy for traditional
conservative people who are saying
you know um you know take your kid you
know you know
that that parenting is like
um especially for mothers just as that
intimacy with the child is so
essential yeah it's essential for their
development it's also excruciatingly
painful
to become uh what is the the abject
you know to to be the thing that the
child has to reject
to become the thing that is that you
were like as the child repulsed by
which is the which is the sacrifice of
the mother the mother has to become that
which the child revives
like reviles and in order for the child
to
either eroticize or become you know the
phallus right
so this behavior of conflict you know
between these three principles you have
the father the mother and the infant
like there's tension as much as there is
symbiosis
between all of those different aspects
of the family
and the mother plays this very critical
role in the beginning of life and she
has to
accept that she will become the evil one
you know she will become the devouring
mother to the child because the child
must leave her and that transition is
painful
and in fact we're actually aided by our
evolutionary history
in being given repulsion the child is
given repulsion
by their body to get them away from the
mother to take the risk to leap into the
world
and leave her behind even though that is
painful
you you kind of delay experiencing the
pain of that because the repulsion
moves you to get away from her and you
have to endure that as a mother
like and and i think a lot of mothers
especially of this previous kind of
generation
the generation that raised me for
example did not let this happen
they wanted to be their children's
friends and they wouldn't
they were not satisfied with the idea
that they would become evil to their
children
and so they attempted to smother them
and that is also part of what we're
dealing with which is like
didn't bother
[Music]
so to become fully conscious of all this
stuff i think really
is difficult really difficult to face
especially if you
are in a time where you know you believe
in this kind of like
you know everybody gets along and you
know there's a perfect socialist utopia
that we can construct using the
government
and through technology and no one will
ever have conflict with one another
it's like no literally at this like kind
of this fundamental
dot like triad of the family
we have both synergy but also tension
and that is i think
principle principle of reality that we
cannot escape from
and to be conscious of this um as a
developmental factor
and to put yourself into it as a woman
to say
look not only am i going to sacrifice my
you know
the opportunity cost of having a child
um in terms of career or in terms of
like seeking
opportunity elsewhere i'm going to go
through nine months of pregnancy which
will er
irrevocably change my body and then i'm
going to
sacrifice my time to raise a child and
then that child
inevitably is going to turn away from me
and may actually vilify me
and that this will go on for potentially
over a decade
that might lead to hysteria i mean i
don't want to say
it's a cliche right just talk about
feminine hysteria but but
in a way you can see where it where
where it could it could come from
i have a different take on feminine
hysteria
actually so i think that's happening
can i just stop you for just a sec i was
thinking there's
there's a few people left here i don't
know how many people are are on facebook
and it's
um and i've been meaning like in the
past 10 minutes to maybe open up the
the conversation uh so other people can
join in so
um since there's there's three people
still here a few people left and there's
three people still here maybe
we could have just an open conversation
and i could ask other people
to turn on their cameras and and unmute
themselves and join in
um or if you feel uncomfortable about
you know doing that you can always
uh put your put some questions uh in in
the chat box
hi tom well we have joe and and joseph
here
um um so i i apologize i interrupted you
rachel do you would you wanna we were
talking about feminine hysteria and you
you were talking about your take on that
yeah well i think um what was considered
like hysteria then
is um like kind of like people called
every woman borderline now
like people called every woman hysteria
historical then
um and it's just like women who are
going forward in a way that isn't
considered to be like
proper you know i'm not to say that
historian borderline don't exist
um but they're often like blanket terms
can i qualify that a little because i
don't want to sound you know
i think you know the freudian idea is
what hysteria is the emotional
uh you know um craziness and neuroticism
is mental craziness right you know and
and and
men i probably tend tend to more
ideation
craziness and and women tend towards you
know the more physical
you know for obvious reason craziness i
just mean it i don't mean that all women
are like that i mean that's a tendency
uh probably
okay right but on the other hand i i
want to also say that i think that
there's
there's a positive kind of hysteria this
kind of fiery energy like that
you know paglia seems almost like it's
staring when she talks right she's
she's like almost possessed by something
and that that could be uh
right right and it's important for us to
distinguish between these two types of
hysteria
we have on the you know shamanistic
expressive
poster i don't think that should be
called hysteria we we should regulate
hysteria to
what what you're talking about the
unhinged and
the forgotten the gone you know um
emotions take charge and there's no
longer
like any rationality at all like that is
hysteria on not creativity you know not
just going wild and letting oneself go
um but i don't think that should should
be called hysteria but a lot of people
yeah and freud when he talked about
hysteria he was talking about the
victorian age when
reality was was very much repressed so
so that was part of it as well right
yeah yeah i think it conservatives are
too quick to label women as
hysterical just because they like say
something that doesn't seem feminine
enough
you know i would never do such a thing
no
no not you no yeah many not not all
conservatives
[Laughter]
i don't know i don't know if i'm a
conservative i don't know if they ever
like rachel's book is called the the the
new alt right and you've
you've identified with the right in some
way and you seem to be sort of
like a radical artist like some of the
people i i knew in the 90s who were
always
always on the left and the left used to
be all about free expression and
and uh and uh and uh live and let live
and and whereas whereas today it seems
to be almost the opposites like
we talked about that also this inversion
i i just want to be
clear my book is the new art the new art
right
not there's no alt yeah
right i i thought i said art great but
yeah okay so it's the new art right and
it's about art being
lifted out of the norms of political
correctness
it's about having a vitalist movement of
the spirit
it's about using the ideas of
hierarchy and tradition in an occult
sense in a metaphysical realm
creating an aesthetic right an art right
a creative
vitalist right and that's what my book
is about it is definitely um
not traditionally right-wing um and you
would think people would get it you know
because they have the word art
before the word right but some people
think it's like some traditional
right-wing
book and then they read it and they're
like no that's not it um
so so yeah um and the reason that
the left has lost that creative vitalism
that you speak of that was very
prominent
you know left-wing 90s art movements
um well i mean look at me blame it on
like neoliberalism like social justice
corporatism or is it just the times they
are
changing um i don't know but i think
that it's time for us to explore a more
vitalistic and aristocratic type of art
that isn't regulated
to activism and political correctness
cool does anybody uh any of you guys
want to jump in with some questions
for the philosopher queens
we won't devour you i promise tom you
must have a question for us of course
joseph seems to be unmuting himself
joseph
you have a question joseph tom has
something to say i can wait
yeah well i always have a lot of
questions
so so raven so just like how do you jive
with those portlandians you know social
justice
or as feminists i don't drive with them
i stay away from them is that true
yeah i mean why would i i mean i've
mostly found myself in communities of
men
i really haven't had that many female
friends in my life
and the few female friends that i have
made and maintained
are also very intellectual
very curious um women
who aren't uh are kind of outcasts in a
way
they're also kind of outcast in some
some manner so
but that's like very very small group
um like i could count on my fingers like
one hand
like how many female relationships i've
had that have really stood this test of
time
and have also stood my questioning of
like the milieu that we were kind of
immersed in
um i went to the evergreen state college
in olympia washington
like really radical left
like is it that famous one the brett
weinstein one is that
that one that's the one all right um
yeah and brett and heather were my
professors for years
um and i studied evolutionary biology
under them so
like i was always kind of in this weird
uh
like antithetical milieu at that school
but there was all this you know there's
all this tension
and of course i wanted to assimilate but
also it was like learning these other
things that went against
a social narrative and i've yeah i have
one really good friend who's seen me
through all of that
um and she has you know she's much more
left than i am
but uh she's been able to deal with the
disagreements
and differences between the two of us
that's like one
right okay okay you know
because i was wondering and i'm i'm not
sure if i can
you know formulate that thought properly
uh without you know because you know in
recent times i'm thinking
like all these things they have like a
quasi-religious
quality you know it's like um and so and
so it's it's
you can observe it not only in the
social justice movement but also like
say in spiritual things you know where
you see
that because and i hope i don't
phrase that wrong because women have
this
freedom today they are way more
say uninhibited to you know
fall into this kind of religious stage
where they inhabit a
completely new world view say in
spirituality or in politics
without being rational
enough to you know to know
how do i say this you know the the
relativity of it
saying and i don't mean it in a bad way
because i think it's a it's a result
of that historically speaking new phase
we're into where men
you know can't or shouldn't impose their
world view on women anymore
but at the same time it seems to me
as a a subgroup of those women
run amok with their worldview in a kind
of way without
questioning that do you know where where
i'm coming from
and so how how do you deal with that
what's what's your take on that
i mean honestly because because i have
to add one thing because
the problem is that you can't really
talk
uh with and to these women without
submitting to their world view and that
makes a rational discourse like kind of
complicated yeah and they usually have
men hanging around too that are kind of
i don't talk to women like that like i
don't know
act with social justice activists i
don't need to worry
about like sometimes they they mob me
and like like dox me but like that
they're not
in my circle like the issues i have with
women now we're the old
traditionalist ones who make fun of me
for being neurotic and not having
children
like social justice activists they're
not even in my sphere
right i'm dealing with the the other end
of it
i'm dealing with women who who are
looking down at me because i have
tattoos i
like i'm sorry that you have to deal
with social justice activists but like i
don't even think about them
no not not necessarily social justice
activists but
like for me it's if there are social
justice activists or some spiritual
people who have like a
world view of angels and you know this
is reiki and
all-encompassing it's like it's like the
same thing with a different
with a different paint on it you know
it's like that
yeah you know what you're yeah the new
age spiritual
the i mean i call them the chakra click
you know they're the chakra click
they're the
the healing goddesses the hashtag
gratitudes
right they're a mob they're they're a
mod they they have their self
care smoothies and their their healing
crystals and
i don't think that you should interact
with them now if they're coming at you
because really they're very angry deep
down no i don't i don't know
i just don't touch them no i don't i
don't mean it in that way that
i or we we shouldn't interact with them
the question would be the same
like how how you know what would be
the proper step or
or say culturally speaking like for them
you know to have a perspective on their
worldview and
being instead of being inhabited by the
worldview
right because i think that's the part of
a philosopher to say well
there are world views and i can can have
a critical distance
to it and i can if you're a good
philosophy you can even have like a
critical distance and you should to your
own worldview
and that then then it gets interesting
but if you talk to social justice
warriors or
new age people and i think with men it's
the same
but it's like if you're inhabited by it
and you can't have a critical distance
then like a discourse is really
problematic
problematic right
so what yeah what do you do from from
from i think that's really problematic
what you said tom
i i just think that it's best to freedom
of association
like don't go to events that they're at
like
don't talk to them maybe that that
sounds dismissive
i'm not trying to be dismissive here
it's just you know
you've got like 10 women you can talk to
you know and
and two of them are interesting logical
rational and you got eight of them
talking about like the healing goddess
of the moon
and like the vaginal painting of the
whatever
like would talk to the two like that i'm
still i'm still not
i don't mean that personally you know i
i i i just mean like what can they do
no it's like as a cultural as a cultural
development so
women have this freedom now to choose
their worldview and
but you know it's like in in human
histories of time
it's like a really short period when
they can do that
like 50 years and so it's like okay we
had like say
40 000 years of male dominated world
views or whatever
and so and so suddenly females are able
to to do that
but it seems to me at one point that
they're not
have developed culturally you know a
form of critical
and i don't mean that in that way men
majority of men can't do that either so
don't get me wrong
but the point is like culturally
speaking so what
you know how what would you propose what
would be
you know the next step you know i know
how i deal with those women you know
it's not that's not okay
did sue me and for the women i don't
think we should
for the women yeah i don't think we
should force change
upon them we should let them do what
they want right like i don't think that
it's
our job to tell them how to
if i just think that's why i say it's
better to avoid that i'm not
like it's a dismissive answer but
because it's not
our duty to make them more like us we
that that's inauthentic right okay
do i know yeah i mean i i think
i think that also like
women have had their world views in the
past it's just that it was
it was not in the public sphere and then
also i think that
um you know so their way of influencing
was happening within the home they would
you know influence their husbands
or their sons or their fathers to
kind of enact their own political
interests or social interests
women had this kind of soft power and i
see that now operating but it's also
engaged in a public sphere
so there's also an issue of men
themselves
turning themselves away from women and
keeping to their own ideas and not
letting the soft power of women
influence their thinking
because that's kind of where i see
another issue
is that if women are then exerting this
like power
of their kind of radically subjective
experience of their ideas
so having no kind of internal distance
um in into in their interior between
their kind of eye and the world view
that they are
kind of playing around with or or
exploring
the fact that there's no gap there and
that they're radically their eye
and the world view are a singularity in
terms of their internal experience
right not having that gap um you know
and then
because of the sexual dynamics between
men and women and because it's
the availability of women in terms of
long-term partnership is so
scarce you know and that kind of
power dimension between men and women
and the fact that lots of men just like
get in line
to conform to what women want right in
order to
get attention from women because of
course people want attention from women
but like that's just the thing like
people want attention from
young beautiful women and so if those
young beautiful women have certain kinds
of world views
and they'll just fall in line at least
on a preference falsification level
in order to get you know get the view
get that eye you know get that
experience get that attention for
validation
um so it's both
things in terms of like men standing on
their own
not falling into the gays not kind of
getting caught up in the limerence
um and conforming themselves to what uh
women want and then women themselves i
think that this is part of why like you
know the philosopher queen manifesto is
not written as a
as like a kind of evangelical like here
we're going to convert all these women
but it's like we are just standing out
here and we're going to start modeling
this
and if you want to join us join us right
you know through mimesis
like you can you can come and join us
but like i'm not going to go out with my
bible and like
thump it to try and convince other well
that's just a waste of my time honestly
like i think
you know both rachel and i have
identified this and i think it's part of
why
i've been attracted to accelerationism
and um
arts exodology like exit
okay like voice is like totally
it's been so it's like the like debased
you know the idea of voice is just like
completely flat
everybody gets the same platform online
everyone has the same value in terms of
their voice
and it's like why why
why participate in that when you could
exit
and engage in these back channels and
then i think that's also
something that's just different things
hidden aspect
of like these communities online that
are going underground
right to have real discussions to really
dig into controversial ideas
like that's where you want to go right
like i was thinking about
that in modernism and i was thinking
about something
that hanzi said um i think it was on the
gem rat podcast about how we need an
anti-populist politics
and that we need to be here it is
political metamodernism is the opposite
of populism so what we don't need is
the the voice we need the exit like
raven says we need original founders
getting together
and forming new societies we don't need
power brokers appealing to
populist sentiments to win old societies
that society is is
old um we're not going to conform to it
we want to create a new society that's
going to confirm to us we're
pioneers we're visionaries we're leading
a new way right
i mean in germany you would get canceled
for that that's for sure
you'll get cancelled yeah i i don't know
like
i've been cancelled quite quite a bit
i'm still standing
still you don't exist unless you've been
cancelled you have to be canceled don't
you i mean in order to be somebody
really i mean i think anyway
i mean god like who wants to be who
wants to
live up to whatever expectation that is
um well it's like it occurs to me that i
i just had a thought
when all this if you don't mind me
jumping in again but
it just occurs to me that um for a
movement
to to to be integrated there's always
there's always
there's always this powerful attraction
of of women right young women
as you were saying there's always and uh
and i think
a lot i've been doing men's work i think
the building of male male character
seems to be very very very important
here because it's so easy to become
um seduced to be to be a sort of uh you
know uh
a slave to that in a sense i call it a
simp
a simp right exactly what it is
you become a slave to that and and i
don't get that watch the sim
yeah what's the symptom it's a
term for like a man who basically like
you know
worships a sort of internet goddess
figure
worships internet goddess figures it's
sitter's
at the same time i want to say we need
these women at the uh
with these these powerful magnetic women
to to
create this let's say um artistic
movement
in the whole thing so it doesn't remain
male and intellectual
like uh it usually remains if it's just
a bunch of men it
online especially it becomes extremely
autistic it seems to me
on some level right um me and joe
joe's down below we have this thing
called the forest philosophers in
avon france and and uh and we don't
we're not online at all we just
we're we're we're a salon like we just
started and
we're just offline right because i think
the online
world is especially the male world is so
um yeah so so male and autistic
whereas the real movements i remember in
the 90s there was always this kind of
you know night polarization dynamic and
creativity between men and women which
i feel lacking and is one of the reasons
why i kind of like i get excited by
hearing you guys talk because
there seems to be like this fresh breath
of fresh air
in
you can't hear you joe yeah
oh no okay well you can try and figure
it out
and uh here we go you're unmuted i can
ask you to unmute
uh in the left-hand corner yeah there
you go okay man
beautiful we got you great you know just
to follow up on that
um you know breaking down on the
categories of uh philosopher
i i'm coming from the art world and
rachel what you were saying about
you know the poets and kathy acker and
you know and i'm just thinking about the
um
in utility of having these category
categorical
uh distinctions that aren't necessarily
necessary at all you know so if you take
something
like kathy and going back to somebody
like urchin stein
um juna barnes you know where women were
really
um not only creating the movements for
at the forefront and in in
breaking the categories and not
getting into any um hierarchical
um linguistic uh distinctions
you know so like when when i think of
like queen right like philosopher queen
i mean isn't that linguistically putting
you into a hierarchy of some sort of
thinking that you know at the beginning
of this i i think
raven you said um you know what would
happen
if women were in the huts what what sort
of language would we
have emerging from that you know these
are
sort of the i i think we have too many
false distinctions
and i i think we get too um too
concerned
with um going into
uh you know camps of
of of of uh you know i i this is where
language breaks down
and it's like where does art and
philosophy
intersect is like you know
a concern that i have um you know so
where where are you what are you guys
thinking about that
well i think that it's okay to use the
term philosopher queen because
it's not about getting people into a box
it's about
putting people in a place where they
feel free to express themselves
free thought has always been my top
priority and i believe that
it's raven's top priority or one of her
top priorities too it's about freedom of
thought
um and so that's why we created blessed
earthquakes for freedom of
fact um freedom of expression freedom of
gender you know free freedom um
that's a really important thing to the
arts the philosophy the culture
um so you know terminology though you're
right it does have a tendency to get
bogged down
and you know wants you to find something
you know i'm good good luck keeping it
what it is
i'm sure that in like 10 years from now
we'll have philosopher queens for
people that would like to file their
original message and like we've been
kicked out and we're like no longer
philosopher queens and we hate what it's
become
but that's like every group that's like
every subculture that's every movement
that's every political party
um the things change things evolve
things take on new forms and
you know if philosopher queen becomes
something that we're against um we can
either like
fight for the term or you know forge
forward with a new term and
i don't know it depends on the the
instance
so i really i do appreciate what you're
saying um
and it doesn't make a lot of sense why
you would have these concerns and i have
these concerns also
i think that um i don't think we're
necessarily
anti-hierarchy either
um i i think that there's definitely an
elitist streak
in both rachel and my philosophy
and the queen also invokes the matriarch
um the the most powerful woman of the
community
and i think that there's almost a
hyperstational quality
to the invocation of the philosopher
queen i wouldn't consider myself
at this time a queen um i would consider
myself working towards becoming the
matriarch
and there is a commitment to the process
of
generating what what is the wisdom of
the woman right
um and how that derives and arises out
of the body of the woman
and what she is kind of tasked with
throughout her life
and i think for me the attraction to the
concept of queen
um is of
that matriarchal figure of like the
grandmother
you know of like the woman who has
children and grandchildren and
great-grandchildren who
guides the other women throughout all of
these different developmental processes
in their lives
and also you know gives guidance to
the patriarchs when they need their
their
the wisdom of the women to guide them
and so i think that that invocation
is an invitation for women to consider
themselves
as more than princesses you know uh
as as more than just like wanting to
have people lay at their feet
wanting to be giving gifts wanted to be
kind of
treated with this um kind of
goddess-like
worshipping the queen is not someone to
be merely worshipped but she wields the
power of the sovereign
she wields the power of the sovereign
and that is a grave responsibility
but you have to prepare yourself for
taking on that responsibility and it's
not something that you
you know give to yourself it's like
something that is
given to you you know i was surprised
like when people began to
you know because the philosopher queen
you know rachel and i philosopher queens
is like to be given that
title and to be recognized for that
title
and you know to give it to oneself i
think is a completely different
um dynamic but to invoke it in a
hyperstational manner and then to be
seen in that manner
means that we're rising you know we're
rising to take on the responsibility of
the matriarchy
um and that's not something that is
equal to
being a princess you know that's
something that is uh
on par with with the men
holding their kind of patriarchal order
as well right it's definitely not an
anti-hierarchy manifesto i mean i talk
about how we're
a new order that's beginning to take
shape
i talk about how we're under current a
new current
um like i say you know this is not
neoliberal feminism this is american
life this is a return to the energy
that has been repressed for so long
you know like we are and have always
been the invisible cabaret
throughout centuries we have been
worshiped demonized obsessed over and
loudly ignored yet it is time for
a new rising it is time for a new
archetype
it's an invocation it's an invocation
of the philosopher queen archetype i end
it with
we are philosopher queens and we deliver
this legend
it's creating a mythology for
women to express themselves in this new
realm
and it definitely isn't about them
creating uh equality or something like
that
how much is that embedded anyhow in in
in your work like hermeticism
heminotics archetypes mysticism
like um could you elaborate a little bit
on that
which one of us whoever the other one
do you want to talk about that cult
rachel oh yeah talk to them
yes please yeah i just i hear i hear
like a little
i hear a little buzzing oh it's gone now
okay
um so yeah so the the occult is the
the hidden the tonic the often forbidden
that which
is not on the surface the mysterious um
so
how do people express the occult through
art
through literature through music
through dance through theater those
hidden elements
become expressions of the human core
um whether somebody is using a metaphor
to describe an occult experience whether
somebody is writing
esoterically to describe a
metaphysical phenomena that they do not
want to write about
literally these are nominated
being through our
sacred esoteric usages of metaphors and
symbols
and dance movements and even
like musical groups like
yeah buried near near andrews andrew's
place because you mentioned dentist
dance movements
yes yeah
you know not not the exposed not the
external that that which is hidden
and what we do um like as artists
is find a way to express the hidden
in a way that still maintains
its mystery and mystique without giving
it all away
yet still being able to bring it to the
table
would you say rachel you're like more of
a poet and ravens more of a philosopher
because i i get this
the feeling when you're speaking that
you're you're kind of almost
um you're speaking in in in
in a kind of language the language of a
manifesto language like a channeled
language or something
and then and then it's it's kind of a
nice balance and ravens
speaks she has this sort of clarity and
um
and uh it's very i find that very
interesting that uh
between you two guys well would you say
that nietzsche was a philosopher or a
poet because he spoke like that
all the time oh yeah okay maybe that's
it
that's a false uh dichotomy or even
somebody like well but nietzsche was the
high water mark on
german literature so that's kind of
complicated with nature
if
there are a lot of philosophers that
grow with the vitalistic impulse
it wasn't just just ninja he wasn't the
only one
that did it on renee and i mean like
this way
like writing his sister and they were
poetically there was a pre
there's a curse a precursor to each
other it was called novalis
um what what about um even the
um mishima when he wrote confessions of
the mask it was poetic
does that mean he's not a well he was
masturbating he's a little
more of a poet than a philosopher right
but what i'm saying is that there's like
a
lot of you can you can be a poetic
philosopher of course
um everything doesn't need to be
academic and dry
you know um and raven she's you know
more
like on the logical end of things but
she also speaks poetically she also uses
creative language she's not
you know like stiff and and dull
i'm and then i think that the stiffness
the dullness and the stiffness is like i
don't i don't like that camille collier
writes like the
very poetic yeah okay have you read
camille she doesn't write like a stiff
you know this is philosophy has room to
be poetic philosophy should be
poetic no i i didn't mean to say what i
what i meant to say was that
from from the viewpoint of the mastery
of the german language
there was nobody better who could do
that than nietzsche basically
yeah like nobody'll ever be better than
him no no no you can discuss
that you can discuss the philosophy of
course but you know this mastery of the
language it's like
that's so beautiful that's so masterful
it's like there's nobody else
and that's just what i wanted to point
out
yeah oh yeah fully fully agreed
i didn't mean to put you into like
strict categories of types or anything
like that huh
you know because because we don't know
each other that well but i i i'm on
andrea
that you speak rachel and the way that
that raven speaks and i'm observing a
kind of
symbiosis and interesting yeah
yeah that's
yeah definitely like she she keeps me
like in check the raven reigns me in
um because yeah it's like chaos and
order or something
i can get quite poetic and perhaps a
little hysterical in the positive sense
of the word um
and you know raven is very good at
grounding you know
and she's very good at getting to the
root um
which is one of the reasons that i love
having raven in my life
because we have so many similar ideas
and interests
yeah we approach it from different
angles where she definitely is more
grounding and i am definitely
more i guess um poetic like like you
said
um and we're able to communicate
dynamically
because of this and i i love having this
relationship with raven
for that reason yeah i've noticed a lot
of things
like what i noticed so it started to
interrupt again go ahead i don't know
a lot of duos recently like people who
are showing
up in two instead of one like i've
noticed like like uh
people have forming kind of powerful
writing teams
you know like yeah yeah the dyad
i think it's a very important form the
people are writing like in in twos now
instead of ones that
that that that's not celebrated enough
in
in our society or or you know co
people who write books together like i
don't know de luz and guitare or
bard and sonicus and you know john
vervicky and his friend christopher well
those guys you don't want to talk too
much about alexander okay no
we talk about him well i i like him
around here
[Music]
shared vision with different forms of
communication
i mean you know like even like if you
have like two people playing in a band i
remember like the the dresden dolls when
they first started it was amanda palmer
just the vocalist and then the other guy
jason lovely i think it was
you know um like he did the harmonica on
the clarinet
you know um and they both have the same
vision for the band
um but they were communicating
differently one through vocals and
one through a bunch of circus
instruments you know um so
so diets are so crucial you know when
people could share visions
you know like it is so important to have
these these different
mediums you know like transmitting
these messages and i think that that's
the beauty of the the diet
and i wonder if if arts and literature
and philosophy will be
move more in this collaborative you know
direction in the future there'll be more
sort of like
i don't know because of the internet it
somehow has this ability to fuse
together minds right
they might do their work outside the
internet that think on
on a similar wavelength and so people
are kind of meeting each other in a new
way
um it could be that could be a positive
thing or also a diabolical thing as well
you know it could be
if that makes any sense and those
yeah yeah like it's almost like marriage
this
yeah yeah creative marriages yeah
yeah i think we're seeking that i mean
the stability of the dyad
um and the recognition of like
you know that the the i mean i really
love this that
barton and it like kind of uses the word
individual rather than individual like
the divisional is like
kind of an emergent property of of the
tribe but the tribe is fundamental
and we have this perception of ourselves
as individual
and we go through this individuation
process but there's
always this like kind of the ground of
which we emerge
is the hyper object of the tribe and by
extension the hyper object of humanity
itself
which is of course nested within you
know in is
principally nature so it's um it's
interesting i think how people are
seeking stable forms
in a time where there's all of this kind
of uh chaotic instability happening
within hierarchies
that is the emergence of these very
simple kind of
um almost molecular bonds right you you
have this
dyad that's very powerful strong you can
create
relationships that are built on high
levels of trust
where through this commitment you can
speak
truth you can you can expose yourself
in the secret world which kind of goes
back into the occultism for me which is
like
on the internet kind of privileges this
notion of status that is associated with
celebrity it's about the exposure of
oneself
and it has completely um cannibalized
the private realm
you know you can go online and watch the
total exposure of the family
like people who literally like live
stream all of their family dynamics
you know that realm which is the most
private has become
the you know kind of voyeuristic
pleasure
of people viewing from far away the most
interior kind of private realms of human
behavior in existence
and that's just one particular example
there's this like drive to expose
which i think has a hyper normal kind of
quality to it because that would have
typically been that which was hidden
and so as as humans we're kind of
seeking you know ooh
the hidden thing is revealing itself now
i must watch
you know now i must look it's very
interesting as this connects to the
beginning of digital libido which is the
discussion of the breast
right the exposed press you know
historically it's like in
in most cultures that like we would be
familiar with
uh maybe not france i i actually don't
know maybe a little bit more liberal
there but
you know the exposure of the breast was
like whoa
okay what is that right holy
we're seeing this thing that's very
anomalous like it's like watching a
fight or something you like you
stop and you're alert and you're like
kind of animal nature drop
comes in and you just want to watch it
you can't help yourself because what's
hidden what's hidden is the most
powerful thing
i mean it could be a breast or it could
be something else right
yeah that revelation is this moment
where all of the eyes freeze
their attention is enraptured by this
revelation
but we've kind of reached the saturation
point in terms of
the exposure of things and i think for
many
communities who are interested in being
continuously on the edge
they're actually cloaking themselves
once again
they're creating a kind of uh bard
absolute i would say
in terms of penetrating into their
communities like you can't get into the
discord server or you can't get into the
email
like threads you can't get in unless you
know someone
or unless you've proven yourself in some
way like that's a kind of cloaking
of that which has been maximally exposed
on
you know public forums such as facebook
or twitter or youtube
um where it's like principally about
that maximum exposure and the maximum
appeal
um and so i think that's where this
you know interest in the occult seems to
also have this
parallel principle of learning agreed
that which is secret
learning how to create secrets for
oneself
learning how to create relationships
where you can build a secret world
and interrogate and antagonize within
this membrane
in order to build something really
strong
before the revelation before that
exposure
of that of that thing um which is a
skill set you know it's a skill set
it requires maturity and that's exactly
what the growth process
is it's to engage in these like
marriages
where there's this you know entitlement
in a marriage
you also create a secret language don't
you and and that secret language has an
occult
quality in it absolutely and that that's
that that's what
that that can't be um expressed to
anyone else it lives in a private realm
right and i guess i guess that's exactly
true what you're saying that that
this this extreme exposure of of every
taboo
right at least visually is like it's
like okay now we have to bring back
taboo or something we have to bring back
uh you know we have to bring back the
hidden the secret the
the occult but
yeah a little sense to me at what you're
saying
and also what's coming up too is like
you know i think we kind of all gather
around the
you know the sons of these massive
philosophical kings
like hegel or nietzsche you know and
we're just like
praise be but these are not only
these these are not the only people out
there like there's a lot of people
cast in their shadow and i think that's
also the occult path
which is to go in and look for the
people who haven't been placed on this
like
level of celebrity um that towers above
all else and i think that's where most
of the women philosophers exist
i think my experience the deepest people
are
would never expose themselves to public
scrutiny
in any way like the deepest people i've
met right
like are hidden the deepest people are
usually hidden and there's a very good
reason for that it's
because if they did this people were to
go too much on the surface they would
sacrifice who they were
to appeal to people who didn't
understand them they would be putting
curls before spine
it's better for them for us to be in
small groups communicating among people
that we connect with not watering down
or dumbing down our message for
the public i would much rather have a
small
group of philosophers that i can
communicate with
on a very personal realm then be in
front of a huge crowd of people who i
need to
develop some you know fake message
for in order to like appease their
sensibilities um
yeah i'm not a fan of that i think back
to like the the anarch
you know the self-sovereign individual
and um
how important it is to meet other people
that are so sovereign you know and for
us to not go out
into the public and and join the
spectacle but for us
to have deep intimate gatherings with
one another
yeah guys i hesitate to
to bring this to an end because i think
that it could go we could go on for
for a long time i think it's been a
wonderful conversation
um we have about five minutes left so so
i was wondering if if
if you want to leave our listeners with
something i mean this will be
uploaded to youtube of course and and
it's being streamed on facebook
so god knows who's watching it there and
uh
that one commentary guys nothing
personal but we were attacked by a troll
earlier um uh in any case uh
uh um uh is is there anything like uh
you wanna final final thoughts final
um you know something you wanna you
would like
to share with people
i don't know hmm hmm
well you know i think um if if anyone
out there
is feeling provoked called i mean even a
negative
reaction is a is a reaction and tease it
out
you know like figure it out for yourself
see if that's something that someone
else
put inside of you you know a thought or
a reaction that doesn't belong to you
like i think that taking on the
responsibility for your own thinking
and not blaming society for giving you
bad ideas
like ultimately you are responsible for
your thoughts ultimately
you can craft the virtual world that you
would have it inside of your mind
and there are so many people that
want to have these discussions like i
found
myself being completely embraced by the
communities that i have engaged with and
it's it's really amazing to have this
warm welcome
um to to be invited to this you know to
you know both rachel and i
we're on technosocial you know we're
talking about these things people want
to listen
and uh we want to engage more
particularly women but also men in
conversation and are genuinely curious
about women
um i don't think that all men are
misogynists or something like that like
i think there's a genuine curiosity
about what
women are experiencing and what we're up
to
and by having these very mature
lucid conversations and digging into
some of the most
kind of difficult things to confront
because it's not like this stuff is
easy i mean there's some really dark
that we not only have to just like kind
of uncover but we actually have to talk
about you know and we have to move
forward
um because we have to adapt
like the adaptation is of of
significance
right now um we're living in a time
where we're reacting to
shifts that are way outside of anybody's
control
um and that's i mean that's the task
that's the gift
i mean we have the gift of living in
this time
um and to not be open to seeing it i
think is a is
a tragedy it's a tragedy and um
yeah so if anybody out there feels
drawn to the conversation you know just
know you're welcome
rachel i think raven
covered it yeah anybody listening
feel free to contact us we'd love to
communicate with you
um i guess last thing i would add short
and simple don't dumb yourself down
to fit in with other people
don't compromise yourself for your
message
so you can be a part of a clique the
right people will find you
just keep doing your thing stay true to
yourself
okay thank you so much uh thanks for
coming to paralex and thanks for
preaching the holy gospel holy gospel
awesome thank you for having having us
it was really nice to meet you guys like
this
great questions
rachel raven thank you very much for
coming that was amazing thank you
yeah i hope you stay in contact of
course yeah wish you all the best
keep in touch with parallax and we have
some events coming up uh
uh in the next couple days um we'll be
talking with a guy who wrote a book
called
the meaning of being a man which is sort
of the polar opposite of
well the philosopher queens in in a
sense but
and then we also have some uh we also
have bard
alexander bard talking with greg
henriquez on tuesday
another trial so
[Music]
that's what we're up to here wonderful
okay